<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Healthwatch Leicestershire - Public &amp; patient voice for health and social care</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/rss.xml</link>
    <description></description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>New Healthwatch arrangements</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/new-healthwatch-arrangements</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;From 1 April 2018, there will be a new Healthwatch arrangement for Leicestershire and Leicester City. The new provider is Engaging Communities Staffordshire (ECS) and they will be picking up the reins from the start of April.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The current Healthwatch Leicestershire representative positions will end on 31 March 2018 when the contract held by Voluntary Action LeicesterShire (VAL) comes to an end. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;We would like to thank all of our representatives, Enter &amp;amp; View Authorised representatives and other volunteers who have supported our work since 2013 to date.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will be publishing our Annual Report 2017-18 shortly and we will make it available to all stakeholders and upload onto our website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Healthwatch Leicestershire and VAL is proud to have set up and provided an informed voice on behalf of patients and the public on health and social care for the County over the past 5 years and helping to improve services for local people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Contact details for ECS&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;ECS will be offering memberships and volunteering opportunities to all members of the community. If you are interested, please contact ECS on 01785 224819 or email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:aileen.farrer@ecstaffs.co.uk&quot;&gt;aileen.farrer@ecstaffs.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 14:42:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>phil.w</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2256 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Have your say on the Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland draft Joint Carers Strategy 2018-2021</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/have-your-say-leicester-leicestershire-and-rutland-draft-joint-carers-strategy-2018-2021</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recognising, valuing and supporting carers in Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over six and a half million people in the UK are carers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking after a person that you care about is something that many of us want to do. Caring can be very rewarding, helping a person develop or re-learn skills, or simply helping to make sure your loved one is as well supported as they can be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft Joint Carers Strategy 2018-2021 sets out a shared vision and priorities for recognising, valuing and supporting carers by Leicester City Council, Leicestershire County Council, Rutland County Council and the Clinical Commissioning Groups (CCGs) for Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland. Partner organisations that have been involved in the development of the strategy include Healthwatch (Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland), Alzheimer&#039;s Society, The Carers Centre, Voluntary Action South Leicestershire (VASL) Barnardo&#039;s and Age UK Leicestershire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key priorities have been identified to support carers across Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland to continue in their caring role and to maintain their own health and wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have described our planned actions for each priority and we want to know your views on these: this feedback will be used to develop our detailed action plans which will support the Joint Carers Strategy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have your say at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leicestershire.gov.uk/carers-strategy&quot;&gt;www.leicestershire.gov.uk/carers-strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation closes on 22 April 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 11:44:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>phil.w</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2246 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Have your say on proposed changes to residential care and short breaks (respite care) for people for with learning disabilities in Leicestershire</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/have-your-say-proposed-changes-residential-care-and-short-breaks-respite-care-people</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leicestershire County Council (LCC) want to hear your views on proposed changes to residential care and short breaks (respite care) for people with learning disabilities in Leicestershire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The proposals relate to Hamilton Court Residential Home in Coalville, The Trees Residential Home (Ashwood and Beechwood) in Hinckley, and Smith Crescent Short Breaks Service in Coalville. These facilities are dated and their layouts are not particularly accessible for people with physical disabilities. This has affected the number of people able to use the services and presents challenges to delivering sustainable services in the longer term. The overall demand for residential care is reducing as more people are supported to live independently and the Council wishes to expand its short break accommodation, which is not readily found in the independent sector.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;It is proposed to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Close Hamilton Court in Coalville and The Trees (Ashwood and Beechwood) in Hinckley, supporting the 11 residents to access suitable alternative accommodation and services.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Expand the short break facilities at The Trees in Hinckley through closure, reconfiguration and refurbishment of the long term residential services.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Close the 6-bedded short breaks (respite) service at Smith Crescent in Coalville, supporting the 23 people who use this to use facilities elsewhere in the County.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;LCC are holding dedicated workshop sessions for people directly affected by the proposals, including staff employed at the services and relatives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consultation is available at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leicestershire.gov.uk/residential_care_and_short_breaks&quot;&gt;www.leicestershire.gov.uk/residential_care_and_short_breaks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The consultation runs from 19 February 2018 until midnight on 15 April 2018.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2018 11:49:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>phil.w</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2236 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>3 in 1  clinics being trialled in the community for patients with  stomach and bowel problems</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/3-1-clinics-being-trialled-community-patients-stomach-and-bowel-problems</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new 3 in 1 Gastroenterology Clinic is being trialled in Leicestershire for patients experiencing stomach and bowel problems, so they can be assessed, diagnosed and booked in for treatment quicker than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The clinics in Melton mean patients living in the area no longer have to travel many times and long distances to a large city hospital to be seen by a consultant and pre-assessment nurses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gastroenterology is an area of medicine that treats people experiencing problems with the stomach, bowel and digestive system and need further medical investigation to find the cause of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients will have two outpatient appointments. The clinics provide a pre-assessment service on the day of the first outpatient appointment. This means the patient will have all the necessary tests - including a blood test, and health assessment including blood pressure - prior to the actual procedure, called an Endoscopy, which will take place at the second appointment.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An endoscopy is a procedure where the inside of the body is examined using an instrument called an endoscope. An endoscope is a long, thin, flexible tube that has a camera at one end. Images of the inside of your body are relayed to a television screen. The camera can be inserted into the body through a natural opening, such as the mouth and down the throat, or through the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once it is decided that the patient attending the clinic needs an endoscopy, they will be given an appointment time and date for the endoscopy before leaving the clinic. Previously patients would have had to make trips to three or four separate appointments before the procedure could be booked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The patient will also be given a bowel preparation kit and supporting information before leaving the clinic with their appointment date as well as have the opportunity to ask questions of the consultant or nurse ahead of their procedure. Previously patients would not have had such direct contact and support.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a patient has treatment in a community hospital as an outpatient or day-case, this will be arranged by the LLR Alliance. The LLR Alliance is a unique partnership of health organisations in Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland. The Alliance is designed to offer patients more choice about when and where they receive day-case and outpatient treatment and is helping to drive forward local plans to deliver more care in the community, rather than in the large city hospital sites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Helen Mather, Director of Alliance Partnership Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland, said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Internal procedures like an Endoscopy can be very worrying for patients, especially if they have never needed one before. Giving them the opportunity to speak to a doctor or nurse with all the information and a date set for the procedure before they even leave the clinic can provide reassurance and comfort for the patient and their family.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The pre-assessment part of the service also helps us to find out whether the patient is appropriate for an Endoscopy or whether some other form of treatment would be more suitable.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An evaluation of the trials will be carried out with patients and staff in March and, if successful, the services will be rolled out to other areas across Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland in a phased approach.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To find out more about the LLR Alliance, visit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://llralliance.nhs.uk/about&quot;&gt;http://llralliance.nhs.uk/about&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 09:30:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kenton.h</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2226 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Enter &amp; View Visit Report - Lutterworth Country House Care Home</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/enter-view-visit-report-lutterworth-country-house-care-home</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Healthwatch Leicestershire undertook an Enter &amp;amp; View revisit to Lutterworth Country House Care Home on 23 November 2017, following our initial visit in July 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This planned visit was a follow up to observe the care provided, to see if our earlier recommendations had been carried out and was also prompted by local intelligence gathering from members of the public.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Findings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We learnt that Prime Life Ltd had recently acquired ownership of the home on the day of the visit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report highlights the good practice that we observed and reflects the appreciation that residents felt about the care and support provided.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Overall, the residents were cheerful and all we saw were well dressed and the environment of the home was clean and free from odours.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The food choices, individual specialist needs and flexibility of meal times was praised by the residents and family members.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Staffing shortages have been recognized by the new owners and a recruitment drive is taking place.  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;There was evidence of activities involving residents and families, and the manger was enthusiastic to be able to run smaller and more frequent activities in the future.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The group property manager will visit next year to advise on décor that is more dementia friendly.  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our visit showed that there have been changes made since our visit in 2014. The manager and her team with the backing of the new owner are enthusiastic to embrace improvements and changes that will be taking place in 2018. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 16:42:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kenton.h</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2211 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Victims of child sexual abuse urged to share their story</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/victims-child-sexual-abuse-urged-share-their-story</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Victims and survivors of child sexual abuse in Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland (LLR) are being invited to share their experiences with the Truth Project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Truth Project, part of the Independent Inquiry into Child Sexual Abuse, gives victims and survivors the opportunity to attend a confidential session with a trained facilitator to describe their experiences and how institutions failed to protect them. They are also welcome to make suggestions about what can be done to prevent the same abuse happening in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information gathered in the Truth Project sessions will be used to shape the Inquiry’s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NHS organisations and councils in LLR are working together to encourage victims and survivors to come forward and share their experience with the Inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carmel O’Brien, Chief Nurse and Quality Officer at East Leicestershire and Rutland Clinical Commissioning Group said: “We’re appealing to victims and survivors of child sexual abuse living in Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland to come forward and make contact with the Truth Project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Sharing your experience can help prevent these terrible events happening again in the future.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Truth Project was designed in consultation with victims and survivors to ensure each session is held in a supportive environment which puts their needs first. Victims and survivors are able to disclose as much or as little detail as they wish during their confidential session, and they will not be judged or questioned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drusilla Sharpling CBE, Inquiry Panel member and head of the Truth Project said: “Through the Truth Project we can hear from victims and survivors, understand their experiences and learn from them. Their input will help us make meaningful recommendations to help stop the same patterns of abuse occurring in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We will listen to you, we will treat you with respect and what you tell us will inform our work and help us protect future generations.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those who wish to take part can attend a private session at one of the Inquiry’s locations across England or Wales. Victims and survivors can bring a companion with them if they wish. Expenses can be reimbursed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Victims and survivors can make contact with the Truth Project via phone, online at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.truthproject.org.uk/i-will-be-heard&quot;&gt;truthproject.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;, email or by post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is more information about the Truth Project available at the Independent Inquiry into Child Sexual Abuse&#039;s website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iicsaorg.uk/victims-and-survivors&quot;&gt;https://www.iicsa.org.uk/&lt;/a&gt; or via the information line on &lt;strong&gt;0800 917 1000&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;***&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Independent Inquiry into Child Sexual Abuse is examining the extent to which institutions and organisations have failed to protect children in England and Wales from sexual abuse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Inquiry will make recommendations for change with the aim of ensuring institutions will do more to protect children from sexual abuse in the future. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Truth Project, which is part of the Inquiry, gives victims and survivors of child sexual abuse the opportunity to share their experience of abuse with a trained facilitator in a confidential setting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Truth Project aims to put victims and survivors’ needs first. They can share as much or as little information as they feel comfortable with and suggest measures that might protect children from sexual abuse in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Truth Project is accessible by car, bus and train.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The information line is open weekdays 8am-8pm and Saturdays 10am-12pm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NHS and local authorities involved in promoting the Truth Project in Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland include: NHS East Leicestershire and Rutland Clinical Commissioning Group, NHS Leicester City Clinical Commissioning Group, NHS West Leicestershire Clinical Commissioning Group, University Hospitals Leicester NHS Trust, Leicestershire County Council, Leicester City Council and Rutland County Council.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 13:50:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kenton.h</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2206 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Help to protect yourself from infection and prevent the spread of flu this winter</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/help-protect-yourself-infection-and-prevent-spread-flu-winter</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health leaders in Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland are urging people to protect themselves against the flu this winter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once flu is circulating, apart from vaccination, good hand hygiene is the main way to prevent it spreading.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr James Ogle, GP in Leicestershire said: “Preventing the spread of germs is the most effective way to slow the spread of flu. And it’s easy to follow a few simple steps to help protect yourself and your loved ones this winter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Good hand hygiene is important not only in preventing colds and flu but it also helps to limit your exposure for other infections such as norovirus, which is also prevalent in winter. To clamp down on germs, we urge everyone to ‘Catch it. Bin it. Kill it’: use a tissue to catch coughs or sneezes, and then throw away the tissue. Finally, kill the germs by washing hands properly. You should wash your hands for at least 20 seconds, about the time it takes to sing ‘Happy Birthday’ twice, and make sure to use soap.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“These simple measures can make a big difference and will help protect you, your family and those around you.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hand washing with warm water and soap is the most effective and inexpensive way to prevent the spread of germs and infections. Studies show it lowers the transmission of flu, colds and diarrhoea, both at work and home as well as in NHS facilities. Parents are being reminded to make sure that children are taught how to wash their hands properly, particularly if they’re around grandparents or friends and relatives that are ill. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Washing hands properly should take about as long as singing &quot;Happy Birthday&quot; twice (around 20 seconds)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People who are suffering from an illness such as colds and flu are also asked to try to avoid visiting relatives in hospital where possible, to help prevent infection on the wards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr Ogle continues&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We understand that people will want to visit their loved ones when they’re in hospital, even when they’re not in the best of health themselves. Patients in hospital are more susceptible to bugs and infections, and they can spread fast. We urge anyone with a heavy cold to try to avoid visiting where possible, and when you do visit, please wash your hands properly and use a tissue when you sneeze.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The power is in your hands! – Eleven steps to ensuring your hands are free of potential viruses and infections.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. Wet your hands with water (warm or cold)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;2. Apply enough soap to cover all over your hands. You can use alcohol-based handrub if you don&#039;t have immediate access to soap and water.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;3. Rub hands palm to palm.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;4. Rub the back of your left hand with your right palm with interlaced fingers. Repeat with the other hand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;5. Rub your palms together with fingers interlaced.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;6. Rub the backs of your fingers against your palms with fingers interlocked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;7. Clasp your left thumb with your right hand and rub in rotation. Repeat with your left hand and right thumb.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;8. Rub the tips of your fingers in the other palm in a circular motion, going backwards and forwards. Repeat with the other hand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;9. Rinse hands with water (warm or cold).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;10. Dry thoroughly, ideally with a disposable towel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;11. Use the disposable towel to turn off the tap.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can find out more at:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/homehygiene/Pages/how-to-wash-your-hands-properly.aspx&quot;&gt;https://www.nhs.uk/Livewell/homehygiene/Pages/how-to-wash-your-hands-pro...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 10:30:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kenton.h</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2201 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Community Conversation about What Disabled People Think About Hospitals</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/community-conversation-about-what-disabled-people-think-about-hospitals</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On January 16th 2018, LCiL (Leicester Centre for Integrated Living) and NHS University Hospitals of Leicester are holding a Community Conversation for disabled people and carers, to enable them to share their thoughts about the service offered in hospitals in Leicester.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting will be held at West End Neighbourhood Centre Andrewes St, Leicester, LE3 5PA, between 1:30pm and 3:30pm. Refreshments will be served.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For more information please contact Karl Mayes, Patient &amp;amp; Public Involvement Manager on &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:karl.mayes@uhl-tr.nhs.uk&quot;&gt;karl.mayes@uhl-tr.nhs.uk&lt;/a&gt; or telephone on 0116 258 8685&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 11:45:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kenton.h</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2181 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Vascular clinic now available to patients in the  heart of the local  community</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/vascular-clinic-now-available-patients-heart-local-community</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The launch of a new vascular clinic in Leicestershire marks the beginnings of a three year plan to better support patients with vascular conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Vascular Service, which was set up last month at St Luke’s Hospital in Market Harborough, Leicestershire provides appointments for patients who require a specialist consultation about varicose veins, narrowing arteries, lower leg cramps, poor blood circulation and other vascular conditions that may require further consultation and surgery.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The service is managed by the LLR Alliance but is delivered in the community, closer to patient’s homes. This means patients no longer need to travel to an acute hospital to receive an outpatient consultation for these types of conditions, which previously would have been the case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a range of community based services to support patients who have vascular conditions closer to home.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The LLR Alliance is a unique partnership of health organisations in Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland. If a patient has treatment in a community hospital as an outpatient or day-case, this will be arranged by the LLR Alliance. The Alliance is designed to offer patients more choice about when and where they receive day-case and outpatient treatment and is helping to drive forward local plans to deliver more care in the community, rather than in the large city hospital sites.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The LLR Alliance is a partnership of Leicester City CCG, University Hospitals of Leicester NHS Trust, East Leicestershire and Rutland Clinical Commissioning Group (CCG), West Leicestershire CCG, Leicestershire Partnership NHS Trust and the LLR Provider Company Limited (a group of 90 Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland GP practices). &lt;br /&gt;Helen Mather, Director of Alliance Partnership Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland, said:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We are delighted that this nationally and internationally renowned service is now available to patients in our local community, avoiding the need for them to travel a long distance for an outpatient appointment.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Patients needing support from this service can be quite poorly and find travelling uncomfortable so to make their distance of travel shorter contributes to a better patient experience all round.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinics are being held on the first and third Tuesday afternoon of every month at St Luke’s Hospital. Referrals can be made by a GP or practice nurse. To find out more about the LLR Alliance, visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://llralliance.nhs.uk/about&quot;&gt;http://llralliance.nhs.uk/about&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For interviews or more information please contact Liz Mattock, Communications Officer on 0116 295 4159 or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:liz.mattock@leicestercityccg.nhs.uk&quot;&gt;liz.mattock@leicestercityccg.nhs.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes to editors:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The UHL Vascular Surgery Service is nationally and internationally renowned and has amongst the best surgical outcomes in the UK and Europe.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have treatment in a community hospital as an outpatient or as a day-case, this will be arranged by the LLR Alliance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Alliance hospital sites are: &lt;br /&gt;Loughborough Hospital &lt;br /&gt;Coalville &lt;br /&gt;Hinckley and District Hospital &lt;br /&gt;Feilding Palmer Hospital &lt;br /&gt;St Luke&#039;s Hospital &lt;br /&gt;Rutland Memorial Hospital &lt;br /&gt;Melton Mowbray Hospital&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The list below provides you with some examples of the types of treatment that you can access through the Alliance across Leicester, Leicestershire and Rutland: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Orthopaedics &lt;br /&gt;Plastic surgery &lt;br /&gt;Ophthalmology &lt;br /&gt;Rheumatology &lt;br /&gt;Urology &lt;br /&gt;Ear nose and throat &lt;br /&gt;Gastroenterology &lt;br /&gt;Geriatric medicine &lt;br /&gt;Neurology &lt;br /&gt;Dermatology &lt;br /&gt;Vascular &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 11:38:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kenton.h</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2176 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>NHS England Consults on Freeing-Up £136M to boost Frontline NHS Care by Curbing Prescription Costs</title>
    <link>http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk/content/nhs-england-consults-freeing-%C2%A3136m-boost-frontline-nhs-care-curbing-prescription-costs</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-news-body field-type-text-long field-label-above&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-label&quot;&gt;Body:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-items&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;field-item even&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;NHS England has today launched a public consultation on proposals to rein in prescriptions for some ‘over the counter’ products such as dandruff shampoo and drops for tired eyes, freeing-up up to £136 million to expand other treatments for major conditions such as cancer and mental health problems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div&gt;Ending routine prescribing for minor, short-term conditions, many of which will cure themselves orcause no long term effect on health, would free up NHS funds for frontline care. The consultation does not affect prescribing of items for longer term or more complex conditions&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;or where minor illnesses are symptomatic or a side effect of something more serious.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Over the-counter products currently prescribed include remedies for dandruff, indigestion, mouth ulcers and travel sickness. The NHS each year spends:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;£4.5m on dandruff shampoos - enough to fund a further 4,700 cataract operations or 1,200 hip replacements every year.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;£7.5m on indigestion and heartburn – enough to fund nearly 300 community nurses.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;£5.5m on mouth ulcers – enough to fund around 1,500 hip replacements&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;If patients were to self- care for these three conditions alone, it would save the NHS £17.5 million allowing funds to be diverted to other areas.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read full press release below&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 16:09:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kenton.h</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">2171 at http://www.healthwatchleicestershire.co.uk</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
